<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>admin &#8211; Presidential Task Force on COVID-19</title>
	<atom:link href="http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/author/admin/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 16:04:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Webp.net-resizeimage-9.png</url>
	<title>admin &#8211; Presidential Task Force on COVID-19</title>
	<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>National Briefing, June 2, 2020 – Remarks by Minister of Health</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 16:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3802</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1. The expanding laboratory and testing capacity all over Nigeria and growing community transmission rate both contribute to the increase in the number of covid-19 positives we are observing in...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">1. The expanding laboratory and testing capacity all over Nigeria and growing community transmission rate both contribute to the increase in the number of covid-19 positives we are observing in recent days. We have nevertheless not reached our testing targets as yet and therefore ask all persons who fit the case definition of fever, cough  sore throat, loss of sense of smell or taste to first use a mask or face covering and find the nearest testing CCenter.Those testing positive should report to the nearest treatment facility in the interest of self preservation. We shall include it in our social mobilization and community engagement messaging.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">2. We are working with the National Primary Healthcare Development Agency, to finalize plans on engagement of existing community volunteers and agents to conduct house to house sensitization on COVID-19 at community level, especially in high burden Local Government areas of Nigeria, since about 20 LGAs contribute nearly 60% of our COVID-19 positive cases.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">3. Nigeria currently has a total of 10,578 confirmed CCOVID-19 cases in 35 States and FCT, of which 3,122 have been treated successfully and released, while we have sadly recorded 299 deaths. The COVID-19 burden is, as we know not evenly distributed within the country, with Kano and Lagos bearing the highest burden. A team from the FMoH, led by the ED of NPHCDA and comprising doctors from Departments of Family Health, Hospital Services and Public Health and NCDC, is in  Lagos on an appraisal visit, during which a situation analysis will be conducted. The team will also visit the contiguous Ogun State on the same mission. The visits are in continuation of similar useful initiatives in the past to Kano, Katsina Sokoto, Jigawa, Gombe, and Borno, to share experience and ideas, align strategy and support each other.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">4. We continue to advocate for states to strengthen their response activities and have begun a program to strengthen the capacity of all Federal Health Institutions in Nigeria to deal with COVID-19 challenges in their States by additional training, supplies and equipment. Federal Medical Center Lokoja and University of Calabar Teaching Hospital will be prioritized for deployment of Gene Xpert machines as soon as the test kits are validated by the Medical Laboratory Science Council, so that citizens in Kogi and Cross River State, among others, will no longer have shortage of opportunity to be tested. Our observation is that states are at varying levels of readiness and it is important to re-strategize to meet all citizens at their points of need. COVID-19 is long since a global phenomenon affecting nearly all parts of the world. All nations are working together and I urge all State authorities in Nigeria to accept the reality and also work with each other and Federal Government, and play their part in the strategy to keep the people safe. This includes the decentralization that requires making a minimum of 300 Isolation beds ready, so that the national health system does not run out of COVID-19 bed spaces. As the President has advised, it is best to be fully prepared even if you didn&#8217;t have to   use it. In this regard, the Federal Ministry of Health stands ready to support all States in their efforts to build resilient and responsive systems for citizens in their States. The FCT, for example, is no longer under bed space pressure, having been well supported with assets to meet all levels of care, security and needs.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">5.​ There will therefore be no reason for a COVID-19 positive person to be outside a designated Isolation and Treatment centre, especially with the ThisDay Dome Isolation centre ready to take cases. It will be headed in the introductory phase by the Medical Director of Irrua Specialist Teaching Hospital, one of the most experienced virus disease hospitals in Nigeria. The FCT managed Idu covid treatment centre with 500 beds is also ready.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">6. ​We have conducted an analysis of Health Care Worker Infections and identified critical areas for targeted intervention, to include continuous updates and retraining. More than 13,000 health workers have been trained, which will result in reduced rate of infection, especially in the line of duty. We are collaborating with States to cascade the training to lower cadre workers.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">7. ​A few weeks ago, I announced that Nigeria will participate in COVID-19 drug trial, which the WHO was leading but partly suspended. After consultation with top Nigerian scientists of the Ministerial Expert Advisory Committee, I am advised that Nigeria has something to add to the body of knowledge around these trials. I have therefore approved continuation of the trial, as recommended, under strong precautionary conditions to be built into it. The Leadership of the Ministry also had the first briefing with the Ministerial Advisory Panel of Experts yesterday, led by foremost virologist, Prof. Tomori, and received a series of very useful advisories that will be discussed and shared with Heads of Agencies and Departments of the Ministry</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">8. ​Finally, as we move into the next phase of easing of the lockdown, I urgently call on all, to take responsibility for ensuring that we actively play our role in ensuring that COVID-19 does not spike or bounce up, as has been observed in many countries where lockdown was relaxed. It is important to bear in mind that this phase, more than the lockdown itself, is in the hands of the people, more than in the hand of government. We must fight the spread of the disease by adhering more strictly than ever, to the various social guidelines which have been announced, published and publicized.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​Please wear your face mask in the public, once you leave your house, or even inside your house, if you are not sure of the COVID-19 status of people you live with. Wear your mask on your face, not under your chin; it has no value under your chin. Be very sensitive about respiratory hygiene, wash hands regularly, use sanitizers and observe physical distancing. Open your windows to let in fresh air whenever it is safe to do so.</span></div>
<div dir="auto"></div>
<div dir="auto"><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​Thank you for your attention.</span></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, June 2, 2020 – Remarks by SGF / Chairman of PTF</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 15:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3800</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1. I welcome you all to the National Briefing for Tuesday 2nd June, 2020. 2. ​Today, Tuesday, 2nd June, 2020 marks the commencement of phase two of eased lockdown as...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">1. I welcome you all to the National Briefing for Tuesday 2nd June, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2. ​Today, Tuesday, 2nd June, 2020 marks the commencement of phase two of eased lockdown as approved by the President and announced by the PTF.</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">It must be underscored that the decisions of the President and the guidelines providing the details are both products of a coordinated effort, designed to enable us achieve a sustainable balance between lives and livelihoods.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3.​ The PTF is conscious of the fact there is a high possibility of members of the public seeing the easing as a signal that COVID is gone. On the contrary, COVID-19 is still virulent, dangerous and infectious. Our lives have changed for good and will never revert to what we used to know. That is why we have urged all the employers, employees and leaders of sectors allowed to re-open to diligently comply with non-pharmaceutical measures prescribed in the guidelines and the protocols agreed by State governments.</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">4.​ As we have always maintained, the fight against this pandemic is not a joke and because the science, data and experiences that drive our National Response are constantly evolving, we urge all citizens to religiously implement applicable guidelines at specific phases of the battle.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5.​ It is also important to stress that the PTF shall continue to monitor the progress and keep the option of a review open should the need arise. I therefore urge all sub-national entities with which we have been collaborating to expeditiously factor the guidelines into their decisions and resultant protocols that would be agreed to. I further urge them to strengthen their enforcement and monitoring mechanisms so as to ensure that the desired results are achieved.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6.​ As the PTF focuses on community engagement and risk communication, I wish to re-emphasize that State Governments now have the responsibility to shape and drive the process. It must also be understood that every individual has a stake and a role to play. We must take responsibility. We must be accountable to self and community on our actions. We must adhere to the guidelines issued.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7.​ Shortly after the briefing of 1st June, 2020 (yesterday), the social media was trending with the photograph of two children wearing discarded PPEs (although it is not certain if the photograph was taken in Nigeria). Significantly, that photograph represents a dangerous development. It underscores the need for more risk communication, community engagement and diligence in the disposal of used PPEs on the part of our frontline workers and the administrators. It also underscores the need to broaden the theme and messages in our communication strategy.  Above all, the photograph has left us to imagine what the impact would be, if schools were to be open and they attended school after being exposed so dangerously. Those three children represent a clear danger to themselves, family and the immediate community.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8.​ While we take remedial measures to reach out to medical institutions on this, I use this opportunity to call on all our health authorities to make sure that waste disposal is done in such a way that would not create opportunities for increasing the chances of spreading the virus.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9.​ This afternoon, in addition to the updates from the Ministers, the DG (NCDC) and the National Coordinator shall re-educate on the protocols guiding the use and disposal of PPEs so that the communities and particularly parents will understand the danger.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10.​ Ladies and gentlemen, there is a lot of work to be done and enough for everybody. We must all overcome this challenge together. You must take responsibility. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11.​ Finally, let me thank the gentlemen of the press for quickly digesting and disseminating the critical information contained in yesterday’s briefing. We still have to do more to uplift the knowledge of our compatriots.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">12.​ I now call on the Honourable Minister of Health, DG NCDC and the National Coordinator to update you, before we take the questions.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">13.​ I thank you for listening. </span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/06/02/national-briefing-june-2-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 21, 2020 – Remarks by Minister of Health</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 20:16:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3796</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1. As you are all aware, His Excellency, the President on Monday 18th May, 2020 authorized extending easing of restrictions in Lagos, Ogun and FCT by another two weeks. The...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">1. As you are all aware, His Excellency, the President on Monday 18th May, 2020 authorized extending easing of restrictions in Lagos, Ogun and FCT by another two weeks. The lockdown in Kano was also extended by two weeks, to address remaining challenges to containing the increasing number of confirmed covid19 cases. As we are gradually getting used to the ease of the lockdown phase before we get back to our routine activities, I have decided to focus on the strategic response activities.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2. ​We now have 26 laboratories spread in 17 states. This has increased our testing capacity. However, while our daily testing capacity is presently at 2,500, unfortunately, we are presently able to test less than 1,500. This is due largely to inadequate surveillance and contact tracing in the states. As more laboratories come on board, I would like to use this opportunity to call on state governments to increase the number of surveillance teams so that more testing can be done in the laboratories.  We have developed new Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to track surveillance strategic directions and programmes.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. We are careful about our numbers to ensure that the figures we announce are accurate. Sometimes, there are errors, but we correct them as soon as they are noticed. As at this morning, we have recorded a total of 6,677 confirmed cases in 34 states and the FCT out of which I,840 have been successfully treated and discharged. Unfortunately we have recorded 200 deaths in 25 state and the FCT.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4.​ A curious finding from the analysis of the deaths shows that nearly half of them died at home. Of those who died at home, about 50% did not show any symptom. This underscores my earlier emphasis on the need for those who test positive to report for treatment. I would also advice those who have taken the test and are awaiting result to heed the advisory to self-isolate from friends, wear face masks and observe hand and respiratory hygiene until your result is releases. By so doing, you will be protecting your family, your friends and your community.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. ​As we scale up training of health workers on infection prevention and control, infection among our health workers has reduced significantly. We have trained the 4th batch of Health Care Workers and Patent and Proprietary Medicine Vendors in Kano State. Training and retraining is a continuous process and we shall sustain the initiative. In addition, the Federal Ministry of Health through Nigeria Center for Disease Control had high level engagement with Hospital Services and Secondary health facilities to improve patients’ management and data qualities. State level Infection Prevention and Control (IPC) trainings working with partners to step down trainings at community level is currently ongoing.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6.​ The fact finding team to Calabar has concluded is back and a report has been submitted. I would like to commend his Excellency, Governor Ben Ayadi for his proactive approach. We shall work with the state teams to ensure that we scale up surveillance and contact tracing in the state.  We shall explore the possibility of upgrading laboratories in the state to ensure ease of testing when suspected cases are identified.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7.​ The development in Lagos where doctors are restricting their services to between the hours of 8am and 6pm because of the enforcement of the dusk to dawn curfew by security operatives has been resolved. I have been in touch with the NMA chairman in Lagos State and the State Commissioner of Health. I wish to thank our doctors and other health workers for their understanding. Our health workers are our foot soldiers and we would ensure that they are able to discharge their duties unhindered. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8.​ As I take my seat, I shall remind Nigerians again, on the need to adhere to the advisories which I would like to re-emphasize again. Masks must be worn and washed daily, ironed, where possible and should cover mouth and nose and should not be left under the chin during close quarter conversation. Tissues must be used when coughing, sneezing and then disposed of.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​The stay-at-home advisory needs to be more strictly adhered to and citizens need not undercut the ban on interstate travel by hiding in goods trucks. This is not a battle to be left to government alone but should be a collective responsibility.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​Thank you.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 21, 2020 – Remarks by SGF / Chairman of PTF</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 20:13:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3793</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Thursday, 21st May, 2020. 2.​ As we progress in the first week of the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Thursday, 21st May, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2.​ As we progress in the first week of the extension of phase One of the eased lockdown measures as directed by Mr. President, it is necessary to remind Nigerians of the objectives of this course of action which is primarily to save lives. It is also of utmost importance to remind our sub-national entities on the need to diligently implement the guidelines and to exercise caution in relaxing restrictions in a manner that is capable of setting back the gains already made. Above all, it is imperative for each of us to take personal and collective responsibility.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. ​The foregoing admonition becomes critical as we prepare for celebrations at the end of the month of Ramadan. It is the prayer of the PTF that we shall all celebrate this Sallah and many more in good health and beseech the Almighty to accept our supplication and look upon our Nation and the World, with mercy.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4. ​I, therefore use this opportunity to wish all our Muslim brothers and sisters a very happy and safe Eid celebrations. But as we celebrate, we want to once again caution on the need to wear a mask, keep physical distances, avoid large congregations, avoid unnecessary inter-state travels and observe personal hygiene amongst other suggested safety measures.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. ​The PTF on COVID-19 is pleased to inform you that in order to underscore the seriousness attached to this COVID-19 pandemic, the House of Representatives has set up an Ad-Hoc COVID-19 Committee. In deepening the existing collaborative spirit, we shall work together with the legislature to be more productive and add value to the overall delivery of service to Nigerians on behalf of whom we hold our responsibility in trust.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. ​In the same sprit of collaboration and coordination, I wish to inform you that I participated in the virtual meeting of the National Economic Council with Vice President and all the State Governors. This is coming on the heels of an earlier virtual meeting between the President and the Governors in a space of one week.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7. ​During the meeting, the issue of alignment of their state level actions with the guidelines issued was emphasized. Similarly emphasized is the need for states to diligently implement and enforce compliance. Particularly, I underscored the need for the Governors to provide personal and strong leadership, carry the policy of community ownership to the grass roots and create deeper awareness. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8.​ The Governors were also advised on the decision taken by some of their colleagues to permit large gatherings as such decisions could inadvertently endanger the elderly, the sick and those with underlying factors during such gatherings. The strong advisory from the PTF is that large gatherings beyond twenty persons remains prohibited and should be adhered to.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​On Monday, 18th May, 2020 when we briefed the Nation on the next steps of our National Response as approved by Mr. President. I mentioned that the guidelines for this phase would be explained in details and published. I am pleased to inform you that the document is now ready and the National Coordinator will present it today. This would further clarify any ambiguity hitherto perceived and no doubt clearly let us know where each and every one of us stand in playing our roles to make the guidelines work.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​For sometimes now, the PTF has consistently answered questions and provided explanations on the categories of persons and services exempted from some aspects of these guidelines particularly as it relates to restrictions on inter- state movement and curfew. For the avoidance of doubt, essential workers including our indefatigable medical personnel, diligent journalists, courageous fire service personnel, telecommunications workers, are all exempted.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11. ​The Inspector General of Police has further clarified the categories of essential workers in alignment with the guidelines and has issued instructions to security agents to work on the approved exemptions. With this clarification, we sincerely hope that the persistent complaints of harassment by these categories of essential workers, especially medical personnel and journalists would be put to rest so that we can harmoniously work in battling this pandemic.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">12. ​The PTF COVID-19 urges all essential workers to go about their legitimate businesses carrying with them valid means of identification and to exercise courtesy in approaching security personnel.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">13. ​Through the surveillance system set up by the PTF, we have received reports that Nigerians have been purchasing Hydrxoychloroquine in large quantities. We wish to reiterate that this drug has not being certified for use in treating COVID-19 in Nigeria by the relevant health and pharmaceutical authorities. Self-medication of any kind, is fraught with the danger of increasing risks of avoidable casualties. We, therefore strongly warn against self-medication. If you are sick, please seek medical advice and if you are confirmed positive, kindly self-isolate in an approved facility. The COVID-19 is highly infectious and dangerous </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">14. ​The PTF continues to receive support, donation of equipment and solidarity messages from professional organisations. In this regard, we want to acknowledge the Nigerian Institute of Quantity Surveyors (NIQS), Chemical Society of Nigeria (CSN) and the NNPC and its partner, Messrs OCEA S.A through its Nigerian representative, Mystrose defense Systems Limited.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">15. ​Yesterday, Wednesday, May 20th 2020, served as a stark reminder to the entire world about the severity of the COVID-19 when the World Health Organisation (WHO) reminded the world that we still have a long way to go in fighting this pandemic. According to Dr Tedros Ghebreyesus, the WHO Director General, 106,000 cases were recorded globally in twenty-four hours, representing the highest single day number since the outbreak of the pandemic. This is significant because it brings to realization, the relentless assault, of the virus on humanity.       </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">16. ​For us in Nigeria, the importance of this message is very clear. We need to eschew skepticism about the existence of this virus and its potency, change our behavior and commit to joining hands in tackling this pandemic.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">17. ​I now call on the Hon. Minister of Health and the DG NCDC to update the nation, while the National Coordinator would intimate us with the critical elements of the guidelines.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">18. ​I thank you all for your kind attention.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/21/national-briefing-may-21-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 15, 2020 – Remarks by SGF / Chairman of PTF</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 17:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3790</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Friday, 15th May, 2020. 2.​ When the COVID-19 Pandemic was declared, corporate bodies, development...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Friday, 15th May, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2.​ When the COVID-19 Pandemic was declared, corporate bodies, development partners, individuals, groups, religious bodies , etc rose up massively to make donations in cash and kind. For effective coordination and accountability, the Office of the Accountant General published five bank accounts into which donations could be paid and swept into a CBN TSA account, daily.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. ​Consistent with the open government policy driven by transparency and accountability of the Muhammadu Buhari administration, the PTF promised that details of all cash donations would be publicly provided. I am pleased to report that the OAGF has published the details of inflow into the FGN COVID-19 Eradication Support Accounts. As at 14th May, 2020, the sum of N792,121,613.89 (Seven Hundred and Ninety Two Million, One Hundred and Twenty One Thousand, Six Hundred and Thirteen Naira and Eighty Nine Kobo) has been credited into the TSA account from various in-country sources. I particularly want to commend the sacrifice of some ordinary Nigerians typified by the donations as low as One Naira, which for us comes from the purest of hearts.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4.​ As we progress in our battle against COVID-19, the PTF wishes to extend its appreciation to several other groups that have been supportive in the discharge of its mandate. We must recognize the support of the Nigeria Police leading the armed forces, the intelligence community and the para-military services in maintaining security, carrying out enforcement  and staying in the front lines always.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. ​I also wish to appreciate the Nigeria Airforce for providing the airlift logistics that has made it easy for the surveillance and surge support mobilization by the PTF and the NCDC even at short notice.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. ​Mention must also be made of the offer by the Lagos Chapter of the Federation of Tourism Association of Nigeria (FTAN) to make hotels available to the Lagos State Government for use as isolation centres. Similarly, we recognize some airlines such as Dana, AERO Contractors and Bristow Helicopters to provide support for the movement of logistics and supplies .</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7. ​This morning, the PTF held consultations with the UN Resident and Humanitarian Coordinator and his team to strengthen our coordination efforts with the United Nations System in Nigeria and building especially on their global reach in all aspects of the fight against the pandemic from the scientific, humanitarian and through supply chain management, in the recovery plans.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8. ​The PTF congratulates and appreciates the testimonies of Nigerians who have recovered from COVID-19, which has given us more insights and further strengthens the need to adhere strictly to guidelines issued. However, an emerging issue from all these testimonies is the issue of prescription for treatments. We should always remember that the symptoms of COVID-19 mimics some illnesses we already know but treating the symptoms Is not the same as treating the virus and for this reason, we strongly discourage self-medication. We shall continue to encourage all Nigerians that feel the symptoms to test and if positive, go into the isolation centres for care by experts. We still discourage management of this infectious disease by private hospitals due to the risk of infection.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​On the issue of drugs for cure, I am pleased to inform you that  five states in Nigeria are participating in the on-going WHO coordinated solidarity  trial. At the end of this, relevant health authorities will make statements on acceptable drugs for treating the COVID-19.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​Ladies and gentlemen, for some time now, public discussion has centred on  the need to look inwards for a local cure. Particularly, the social media has been awash with various claims of treatment for treatment of COVID-19 using local herbs. The PTF remains firmly supportive of the development of a cure for this disease. However, we must follow laid down protocols . The NC has been mandated to publish some of these guidelines for public consumption. I do hope this would shift the conversation to the laboratories while we await results for the greater good of the nation.  As additional information, I am pleased to inform you that the WHO recently coordinated a recent virtual meeting from 70 traditional medicine experts from countries across Africa to re-emphasize the recognition of the potency of traditional cure.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11.​ In providing leadership for the fight against this pandemic, Mr. President did encourage State Governments to adapt national guidelines as suitable to their state and expects that such adaptation should be informed by empirical evidence of progress made. The PTF, therefore, urges states that are lifting restrictions which allows for large congregation of people to weigh their consequences in relation to creating opportunities for more seeding of the virus thereby negating gains already made..</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">12. ​The PTF has received media reports about an extrapolated level of prevalence of COVID-19 in Kano based on the number of some foreign nationals that have been evacuated from Nigeria. The PTF team of experts are still on ground in kano and are working round the clock alongside the teams from the State based on scientific and statistical analysis. I urge members of  the public to remain vigilant and seek authoritative information from the public health authorities at all times.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">13. ​We have also noticed a marked reduction in the delivery of Non-COVID-19 related services in our hospitals. You will recall that the Honourable Minister of Health had on several occasions implored our health institutions not to jeopardise offering critical health services to patients who require attention. The PTF wishes to re-iterate this call and request that health service providers should help relieve the burden of disease in the country by offering the required services. As at present records show that we may be experiencing more unnecessary deaths because our hospitals are turning back non-COVID-19 related patients. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">14. ​As we continue the countdown to the end of the first phase of eased lockdown approved by the President, the centrality of collaboration, especially with the citizenry, becomes very imperative. Our National Response has always being guided by the science of the pandemic as well the extent to which applied measures are helping to contain the virus without compromising basic elements of life-sustenance. Going forward, science and statistics shall play major roles in the decisions to be taken. Similarly, Community engagement shall become a strategy of focus for the PTF.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">15. ​Finally, let me say that our preliminary analysis has narrowed down the over 51% of the total number of infected persons to 9 Local Government Areas across the country and all of them are densely populated. This indicates that a critical element of our taming this pandemic is to reduce opportunities for large gathering, sustaining the ban on inter-state movement, the nationwide curfew  and complying with the measures prescribed (wash your hands as frequently as necessary; use hand sanitizers; maintain social distancing, use a face mask or covering in public places).</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">16. ​In the coming days, the PTF shall submit its recommendations to the President for consideration. Until a decision is announced, we advise you to please STAY HOME and STAY SAFE. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">17. ​I now call on the Hon. Minister of Health, the DG NCDC and the National Coordinator to update the nation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">18. ​I thank you for listening.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 15, 2020 – Remarks by Minister of Health</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 17:08:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3788</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1. 193 new covid-19 cases were confirmed in the past day in 15 states- Lagos(58), Kano(46), Jigawa(35), Yobe (12), FCT(9), Ogun(7), Plateau(5), Gombe(5), Imo(4), Edo(3), Kwara(3), Borno(3), Bauchi (1), Nasarawa...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">1. 193 new covid-19 cases were confirmed in the past day in 15 states- Lagos(58), Kano(46), Jigawa(35), Yobe (12), FCT(9), Ogun(7), Plateau(5), Gombe(5), Imo(4), Edo(3), Kwara(3), Borno(3), Bauchi (1), Nasarawa (1), Ondo(1), bringing the total number of confirmed cases in Nigeria over the 5,000 line to 5,162 in 34 States and the FCT. Till date, 1180 patients have been treated and discharged from hospital care and 167 deaths have sadly been recorded. The case gender ratio remains about 70 to 30 percent for men and women respectively, while case fatality hovers around 3%. A steady rise in these figures is what we envisage with more diligent testing, treatment, Isolation and tracing. Ability and capacity to keep up and align these activities with each other will determine the course of events as time goes on. We implore States and partners not to relent,  but to keep up with the pace, which,  in some States will increase well before it begins to decrease.  Adherence to advisory against interstate travel and compliance with other simple measures like use of masks and avoiding crowds will significantly mitigate the burden.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2. The situation in Kano has largely stabilized, thanks to the good relationship between the visiting Federal task team and Kano State Task force on COVID-19, one manifestation of this being the high number of new cases recorded daily from the fact that all labs in Kano are now functioning and clearing the sample backlog, with over 350 tests done daily. The State government has been doing well in opening up more treatment and Isolation centers.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. A strategy document of National Primary Healthcare development Agency is being developed and repurposed for application to Kano; but also to similar high density, high burden metropoles like Lagos  to respond more specifically to the challenges of COVID-19 tracing, tracking, testing, Isolation and treatment in congested communities. If implemented  it could go a long way in addressing many challenges looming before us.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4. An innovation of the FMoH Kano task team is the Training of journalists to take place tomorrow, the aim of which is to ensure reporters are in a  better position to interpret covid-19 related data and information and also learn to take necessary infection prevention measures. I shall use this opportunity to thank His Excellency, the Governor of Kano State for providing the necessary support for the Federal team to function.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. A Federal Ministry of Health team has been assembled to proceed to Sokoto and Bornu on fact finding and support missions; to engage with State authorities and determine material and technical needs. A most immediate probability is the prioritization of these States for the deployment of repurposed Gene Xpert machines as soon as we start receiving the cartridges in a few weeks to bring speed to testing.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. As mentioned earlier  part of the mission in Kano is to assist State pathologists and scientists to unravel the mysteries around unexplained deaths in some States. The tools for forensic investigation have been jointly developed for a uniform approach and balanced results.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7. We were able to persuade Mrs Susan Idoko-Okpe, now popularly known as the Benue Lady, to allow a test sample to be taken to our laboratory for testing yesterday; the result is being awaited any time now and it will be given to her in person. Please note that, while a patient may disclose their result by themselves, the FMoH cannot do so, except with the permission of the one concerned.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8. The annual World Health Assembly, held every year in Geneva, shall begin on Monday 17th May, and hold this year for the first time by teleconference. I shall be leading the Nigerian team to the virtual meeting, the focus of which is expected to be the global spread and response to COVID-19, requirin individual and collective effort</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​Finally, I shall reiterate again the importance of adhering to public health advisories (wearing our face masks, observing social distancing, practicing hand washing or sanitizing, standard respiratory hygiene, avoiding crowds and all non-essential travel). The importance of these and similar measures is such that compliance should be taken as a civic duty and obligation for every citizen, where each should be responsible for the other. As such, enforcement or policing should not be necessary, for what is meant to preserve life and health. Therefore I call for considerate attitude and social adjustment to the challenges we face at this moment.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​Thank you for listening.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/15/national-briefing-may-15-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 14, 2020 – Remarks by Minister of Health</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 19:38:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3785</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1. Yesterday, 13th of May 2020, 184 new cases of COVID-19 were recorded in 22 states. A breakdown of the cases by States  shows  Lagos (51), Jigawa 23, Bauchi(16), Katsina(16),...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">1. Yesterday, 13th of May 2020, 184 new cases of COVID-19 were recorded in 22 states. A breakdown of the cases by States  shows  Lagos (51), Jigawa 23, Bauchi(16), Katsina(16), Kano(14), FCT(10), Rivers(10), Kwara(9), Delta(5), Kaduna(5), Sokoto(4), Oyo(4), Kebbi(3), Nasarawa (3), Osun(3), Ondo(2), Ebonyi(1), Edo(1), Enugu(1), Anambra(1), Plateau (1), Niger (1) with 6 fatalities recorded in the same period. The total number of cases in Nigeria so far has reached 4,971, with sadly 164 fatalities. So far, 1071 cases have been treated and discharged.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2. As we inch towards significant milestones in our COVID-19 statistics, we are looking at all options to adjust our approach to the emerging situation. The Federal Ministry of Health and its Agencies  particularly the Nigeria Center for Disease Control and the National Primary Health Care Development Agency have scaled up training in Infection Prevention and Control, case finding and management, Emergency Patient Transport Systems, Surveillance Outbreak Response Management Analysis System (SORMAS), down to training of hygienists, stretcher bearers and security personnel. This will increase confidence in the health system, reduce instances of Health worker infection and desertion and improve overall performance.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. ​We have also deployed commodities like PPE and other supplies to States and Federal Health Institutions, and in addition continued with supplies to laboratories to forestall much reported delays arising from shortages.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4.​These measures and others are to address the needs reported to us by the FMoH team, presently deployed in Kano, which has also paid exploratory visits to Jigawa, Bauchi and Katsina and is preparing to visit Sokoto and Bornu very soon. Part of the needs already identified is the urgent necessity of on site laboratories with molecular diagnostic capacity, to reduce the presently extended turnaround time for results. Practical, hand-holding personnel training has been requested for some of the health systems, who have had very little experience in the past, with Infectious disease management. To this end, more personnel is to be deployed from the Federal Infectious Disease Specialist Hospital Irrua, while the kind offer of Lagos and Ekiti State Governors will also be drawn upon to send health workers to assist. Stepdown training will be a priority in the entire excercise  to build capacity across the board to the level of community health workers, in the bid to sustain safe and comprehensive delivery of services.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. The Federal Ministries of Health and of the Federal Capital Territory held a ministerial meeting today and agreed on a firm, synergistic framework for collaboration and cooperation to respond to the challenges of COVID-19 within the Federal Capital territory. A joint committee led by the Hon. Minister of State for Health and including their Permanent Secretaries was set up to oversee the ThisDay Dome COVID-19 treatment facility, recently handed over to the 2 ministries. The initial medical team is to be headed by the Chief Medical Director of Federal Teaching Hospital Irrua. The Ministers also paid an inspection visit to the 600 bed COVID-19 treatment center at Idu, a flagship project of FCTA.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. Also slated for special emphasis by Federal Ministry of Health is ensuring continued delivery of routine services in all hospitals in Nigeria. Latest statistics from the (NHMIS) National Health Management Information System, indicate that Out patient visit dropped dropped from 4 million to about 2 million, Antenatal visits from 1.3 million to 655 thousand, Skilled Birth attendance from 158,374 to less than 99 thousand, while immunization services reduced to about half. All these failings have as yet undetermined consequences, which the easing of the lockdown should hopefully address. However, the suspected downside of easing restrictions has to be balanced off by citizens, with collective determination by all of us, not only to comply with protective and prophylactic advisories, but to encourage relatives, friends neighbors and customers to do same. The use of facial covers like masks in places where social distancing may be difficult or impractical, should be emphasized and supported through distribution of masks to the population,  as an act of goodwill. Face masks should in fact become commonplace and I look forward to seeing that cooks, stewards and Food vendors, for example, wear masks, or lose  their customers.</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">I wish to enjoin workplaces to institute such requirements and ensure that all workers are masked and knowledgeable about COVID-19, and by extension, share it with their families and relations.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7. I wish to use this opportunity to thank community, religious and traditional leaders, who have supported Government initiatives by ensuring that their subjects use masks as the minimum form of self protection for themselves and us all. The present rate of community transmission makes even these simple measures helpful.​</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8. ​We shall engage State Commissioners of Health and their staff through IT platform, to continue training and retraining of health workers in States, as more information on covid-19 is received, to ensure learnings and exchange of ideas and experiences of other countries, is shared.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​We have had discussions with multinationals and our development partners such as WHO and Global Fund, to plan our needs, processes and procurements. Funds are also being repurposed for use in the covid19 response to further increase diagnostic capacity and provide personal protective equipment for our health care and other public workers.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​I shall conclude by thanking our Governors for the leadership they are showing in the response to the virus threat and also all our citizens for adhering to public health advisories. The FMoH visit to Cross River State will be scheduled as soon as transport is arranged and to Kogi State, as soon as details are worked out.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11. ​Thank you for your attention.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-minister-of-health/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 14, 2020 – Remarks by SGF / Chairman of PTF</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 15:31:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Thursday, 14th May, 2020. 2.​ From today 14th May 2020, we begin the countdown...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Thursday, 14th May, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2.​ From today 14th May 2020, we begin the countdown to the end of the first phase of eased lockdown approved by the President, so that our economy could gradually reopen. At the same time, we continue our assessment of the level of compliance with the guidelines and the impact on slowing down the spread of COVID 19. In due course, we shall make further recommendations before the second phase commences.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. ​I must, however, state that our initial evaluation point firmly in the direction of a high level of non-compliance which, as we have often warned, portend grave self-inflicted danger. This fact has made it imperative for me to re-echo our call for taking personal responsibility. You must abide with the guidelines (wash your hands as frequently as necessary; use hand sanitizers; maintain social distancing, use a face mask or covering in public places). In addition, you must comply with the ban on inter-state travels, avoid crowded places, observe the curfew and do all you can to STAY HOME and STAY SAFE. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4. ​You will recall that when the new measures were rolled out and published, we ensured that certain economic activities pertaining to food production and distribution were exempted. This, for the avoidance of doubts includes farming activities. We recognize the fact that we are in the planting season and the nation cannot afford to prevent our hardworking farmers from going to their farms. We therefore use this medium to reemphasize that farmers fall within the list of exemptions and urge State Governors, Local Government Authorities and security agencies to please allow them to carry out their activities. Our food security is critical to our national security.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5.​ In the past two days, the PTF has briefed the topmost decision-making bodies of the country on progress, challenges and planned course of action. The objective was to seek further guidance and fresh ideas to improve the fight against COVID-19. The briefing was robust and very helpful in bringing renewed cohesion into the efforts of government.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. ​The statistics on COVID 19 have continued to come out daily and the indications are that our testing strategy is yielding results because we can now give care to those that need it. The PTF wishes to congratulate all our frontline health workers that have collectively nursed back to health, a total of 1,071 Nigerians already discharged from the various isolation treatment centres. These health workers have put in all, even beyond the call of duty, to save lives. We also congratulate all those that have been discharged and urge them to come out and tell their stories. We need to tell Nigerians that COVID-19 is real, that it is deadly and that prevention is better than cure. There is no better convincing and compelling evidence of the reality of the dangers than your experience.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7.​ The PTF reported the progress made with the evacuation of some Nigerians from the UAE, UK &amp; USA. We also informed you about the mandatory quarantine protocol. Nigerians have in recent days been served with different audio-visual clips by some of these returnees. The PTF is saddened by the conduct of some of the returnees who fail to adhere to the conditions attached to their quarantine. I strongly urge them to obey the rules in the facilities and also urge their friends and relations to recognize the contagious nature of the disease by desisting from visiting them. Complying is in the interest of the visiting relation and in the overall public interest.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8. ​The PTF is pleased to inform you that it has facilitated the visit of the national leadership of the Nigerian Medical Association, JOHESU, National Association of Nurses &amp; Midwives, Pharmaceutical Society of Nigeria, Association of Health Professionals and the National Association of Resident Doctors to Kano and Lagos. Unfortunately, due to traffic gridlock, the delegation could not carry out its mission in Lagos and would repeat it in the coming week. This collaboration underscores the importance the PTF attaches to inclusiveness in the battle against COVID-19. It also reassures our medical personnel that they remain a top priority for government in this effort.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​The PTF welcomes the resolution of the Nigeria Governors Forum to take steps to ramp up testing and provide the prescribed minimum number of bed spaces in their isolation/treatment centres. We in turn assure the States that the NCDC will continue to provide technical support and standardization guidelines. It will also continue to firmly</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">pursue its surveillance activities nationwide. We urge the States to recognize the essence of a strong partnership and always allow overarching public interest to prevail.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​Finally, let me remind all Nigerians that in this battle, vigilance is required, self-preservation is important, collective action is necessary and compliance with guidelines is imperative. All these will help us prevent infection. .</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11. ​I now cede the podium to the Hon. Minister of Health, the DG NCDC and the National Coordinator to update the nation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">12. ​I thank you for listening.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/14/national-briefing-may-14-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Briefing, May 12, 2020 – Remarks by SGF / Chairman of PTF</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/national-briefing-may-12-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/national-briefing-may-12-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 15:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3778</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Tuesday, 12th May, 2020. 2.​ Today, the PTF participated in the commissioning of 300...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">I welcome you to the National Briefing by the Presidential Task Force (PTF) on COVID-19 for Tuesday, 12th May, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">2.​ Today, the PTF participated in the commissioning of 300 bed treatment and isolation Centre along with a 54gene laboratory in Abuja. The facility was powered by a consortium of like-minded partners.  On behalf of the PTF and the entire nation, I say a very big thank you to the Sahara Energy Group, the ThisDay Media and Technology Group, CA-COVID, AFC, CCECC, NNPC and the CBN.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">3. ​The world is in the midst of a dangerous pandemic and one key solution to it is collaboration and partnership. The power and benefits of partnerships have been vividly demonstrated in the Jack ma support, the UN One Basket Fund, the interface with Other nations, the intervention by individuals and corporate citizens within and outside Nigeria. The list is endless.  And we say thank you to all of these partners.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">4. ​As we continue to learn the lessons from COVID-19 by fortifying our health systems and infrastructure against present and future pandemics, I wish to remind Nigerians that there is still a lot to be done and investment to make. The PTF mentioned at the briefing on Monday 11th May, 2020 that it had commenced focus on community ownership, guidance, acceptance and implementation in the control of COVID-19. This certainly requires a great deal of investment in strengthening our primary health care system, the manpower and the infrastructure. I therefore call on other corporate citizens and public-spirited individuals to play significant roles by injecting the much-needed investment into the rural health infrastructure. Given the impact of the COVID-19 on </span><span style="color: #000000;">global economy and our national income, it has become obvious that government alone cannot bear this burden.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">5. ​Since the recording of the index case, Nigerians have clamored for research into home grown solution to COVID-19. The PTF, as part of its mandate, has continued to promote research and wishes to repeat its appeal to all our researchers to go through the validation process so as to enable humanity benefit from their hard work and they in turn benefit from the intellectual property rights associated with such research.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">6. ​The PTF COVID-19 at virtually all its national briefings, consistently pleaded with Nigerians for their support and understanding, especially in complying with the advisories and guidelines issued. We also shared our assessment of the level of compliance and the risks associated with non-compliance. I wish to use this medium to once again underscore the imperative of collective survival because the lack of compliance by any person or group of persons poses a threat to all of us.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">7. ​Particularly, the PTF has become aware of the on-going practice of sharing masks and picking of masks for recycling from dump sites. This places a lot of responsibilities on all of us to be self-educated and to educate others. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The following points are emphasized:</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">​(i) With the exception of fabric masks, every disposable used mask is a​hazardous medical waste and should be disposed of properly, preferably by</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">​ burning;</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">(ii) It is very risky to share masks as the virus is capable of remaining on surfaces for several hours and you could get infected;</span><br />
<span style="color: #000000;">(iii) The unhealthy practice of picking up disposed masks for whatever purpose is harmful to both the individual picking it and whoever procures it later.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Particularly, it will be helpful for high risk people such as the elderly and those with comorbidities, to wear masks or face covering and avoid crowded places. As we reminded you earlier, please keep grandchildren away from their grandparents to avoid any transmission. Most importantly, emphatically say no to stigmatization.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">8. ​Let me say once more that the primary responsibility of government is to protect the lives and property of all citizens. On the other hand, citizens have a duty to collaborate with government by shunning risks and actions capable of jeopardizing the protection provided. We shall continue to put in place strategies and measures targeted at flattening the curve of this coronavirus while at the same time urging and persuading you to comply. Our messages are being delivered in different languages and through multiple medium.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">9. ​The PTF continues to urge State governments to align their actions and enforcement with the guidelines provided. The virus does not respect boundaries neither does it respect status. All State Governments are therefore urged to strengthen their monitoring and enforcement machineries in collaboration with the security agencies.  Let me emphasize that we have seen visuals on the social media depicting total disregard for physical distancing in some locations. This is a dangerous journey towards uninhibited spread if not checked. The PTF is consulting with the authorities of the identified areas to review their strategies.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">10. ​You will recall that the guidelines on the reopening of offices directed the management of such offices to take certain steps and put in place policies that would ensure the safety of their staff. Let me remind the leadership of various offices to make such provisions including infra-red temperature guns at entrances, sanitizers, handwashing facilities, social distancing arrangements and ensuring that masks are worn always. This is particularly critical for government offices in high concentration areas such as the Federal Secretariat complex. We similarly admonish individual staff to cultivate the habit of personal safety first, before depending on the general provision.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">11. ​I now call on the Hon. Minister of Health, and the National Coordinator to update the nation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">12. ​I thank you for listening.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/national-briefing-may-12-2020-remarks-by-sgf-chairman-of-ptf/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Commissioning of ThisDay Dome Isolation &#038; Treatment Center – Remarks by Governor of Central Bank</title>
		<link>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/commissioning-ofthisday-dome-isolation-treatment-center-remarks-by-governor-of-central-bank/</link>
					<comments>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/commissioning-ofthisday-dome-isolation-treatment-center-remarks-by-governor-of-central-bank/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 15:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[PTF News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/?p=3775</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The SGF, other Distinguished Ladies and Gentlemen. Good morning. I sincerely appreciate the opportunity to participate in the launch of the THISDAY Dome COVID-19 Testing, Tracing &#38; Treatment Center in...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">The SGF, other Distinguished Ladies and Gentlemen. Good morning. I sincerely appreciate the opportunity to participate in the launch of the THISDAY Dome COVID-19 Testing, Tracing &amp; Treatment Center in our capital city.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I would like to commend the Management of THISDAY Media Group, and their partners, for putting together the team that set up this magnificent care centre, which encompasses testing, tracing and treatment to help in boosting Nigeria’s capacity to adequately contain the spread of COVlD-19 in the Federal Capital Territory and beyond.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As we are all aware since the onset of COVID19 in December 2019, the Buhari Administration has taken all necessary measures to contain the spread. COVID 19 has had an unprecedented effect on the global economy, impacting all nations big and small. Institutions like the IMF have pronounced that the effect on the global economy will be akin to the slowdown experienced during the Great Depression of the 19305. Global growth is expected to contract to 3 percent in 2020,  down from a positive growth rate of 2.9 percent in 2019 which is effectively a 6% contraction.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In Nigeria, our economy is exposed to triple shocks a supply shock, a demand shock and a revenue shock. Permit me to state that we are currently faced with a public health and economic crisis of unprecedented proportions, driven primarily by the 55 percent .drop in crude oil prices between January and May 2020. This unparalleled shock requires that the Federal and State governments along with the organized private sector, work together to address these challenges in order to preserve lives and restore economic activity  and reset the economy of our dear country.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In a bid to cushion the effects of COVID-19 on the Nigerian economy, the Central Bank of Nigeria(CBN) has implemented several initiatives such as the NSOb intervention facility for small and medium scale enterprises affected by COVID-19; in addition to the N1 trillion facility for firms operating in the agriculture and manufacturing sectors. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">We are also working with financial institutions to enable the continuous flow of credit to viable businesses, while putting in place provisions such as moratoriums and restructuring of existing loans under CBN intervention funds, that have been provided to businesses. These measures are intended to cushion the effects of the slowdown in economic actiVity on businesses, while putting them in better stead to help resuscitate economic activity in the country.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I wish to acknowledge however, that our ability to restore the growth of our economy is dependent on how we address the public health crisis brought on by COVID-19. It is in realization of this fact that the CBN recently launched a N100bn healthcare intervention fund. Practitioners in the Pharmaceutical and health care sectors will be able to access finance at single digit rate through this fund.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Our objective is to improve the capacity of our health system to address emerging public health challenges.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Furthermore, in order to encourage greater research and development in Nigeria of drugs and vaccines that would help prevent the spread of the virus, the CBN is developing a framework under which grants and long term facilities will be provided to researchers, science institutions and biotechnology firms to develop the Nigerian Vaccine. Needless to state that if we are to wait for foreign countries to develop their own vaccines, we will be the last in the queue to receive curative remedies for our teeming population.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The Central Bank of Nigeria today challenges Nigerian scientists at home and in the diaspora to go back to their laboratories and develop a Nigerian vaccine.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Once validated by the Health Authorities, the CBN will step in and do the needful for the sake of over 200 million Nigerians now confronted by COVID-19.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Our inability to accurately predict the extent to which the coronavirus could spread, and how long it would last, requires that we build sufficient capacity within our health system in order to contain the spread of the virus, state by state, city by city and preserve the lives of vulnerable Nigerians. This requires that we all come together to support the &#8216;work of the Presidential Task Force in it’s determination to save lives and stem the pandemic. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">It is in this regard that I would like to commend the Nigerian private sector, who have come together under the Coalition against COVID-19 (CA -COVID) to support the government, by raising funds to procure needed Isolation Centres, medical equipment, etc. So far, the CA-COVlD-19 has raised up to N27 Billion to fund these initiatives. These donations are being used to build well equipped isolation centres across the 36 states of the federation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The THISDAY Dome Testing, Tracing and Treatment Centre being launched today represents a part of the support being provided by the CA COVID alliance. These measures will result in the addition of close to 4,000 hospital beds across the country and will serve as a significant boost towards our efforts at containing the spread of COVlD-19. So, CACOVID has equipped and handed over Isolation Centres in Rivers, Enugu, Kwara, Undo, and Borno States.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">It is expected that all other Isolation Centres will be handed over in other States of the country by May 23, 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In a bid to compliment the efforts of the government in providing palliatives to those affected by the containment measures put in place to prevent the spread of the virus, CACOVID is also providing in-kind assistance in the form of food items to indigent Nigerians across the 36 states of the federation. These efforts are noteworthy as members of the Nigerian private sector have stood up to be counted when it mattered most to our dear country.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I would like to once again thank members of the CA COVID alliance for their commitment in meeting the needs of vulnerable Nigerians, especially in these extraordinary times.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I would like to conclude my remarks by thanking President Muhammadu Buhari, the Presidential Task Force on COVlD-_19 ably led by the Secretary to the Government of the Federation, Mr. Boss Mustapha, the Federal Ministry of Health led by Dr Osagie Ehanire and Senator Olurunnimbe Mamora, the Nigeria Centre for Disease Control, and our health workers, who are all in the frontline, working day and night to help prevent the spread of the virus.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I must also salute the work of the Minister of The Federal Capital Territory Administration, Mallam Muhammad Musa Bello, the Minister of State, Dr Ramatu Tijani Aliyu for effective leadership in containing COVlD-19 in Abuja. Your efforts are indeed commendable, and I can assure that the Central Bank of Nigeria will continue to work with you on solutions that can help our nation address this public health challenge .</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I thank you for your attention.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://statehouse.gov.ng/covid19/2020/05/12/commissioning-ofthisday-dome-isolation-treatment-center-remarks-by-governor-of-central-bank/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
